civilservicejobs.service.gov.uk 2019-12-10

# Civil Service Jobs Privacy Notice - Civil Service Jobs - GOV.UK

This notice sets out how we will use your personal data, and your rights. It is made under Articles 13 and/or 14 of the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR). 

## Your data

### The data

We will process the following personal data: 

When you create an account:

  * name
  * email address
  * your employer (civil servants only)
  * your line manager’s email address (optional - for civil servants to verify their employment)

When you create an account to set up and manage vacancies:

  * name
  * email address
  * your employer
  * staff number

Civil servants who are priority movers have the option to create a profile and add:

  * full contact details, including address
  * employer, role, grade and location
  * employment history
  * diversity and inclusion information

When you view a job advert we may automatically collect:

  * your referral source - the website where you saw the job advert
  * details of the pages you have viewed - including how long you spend on a page, and which links you select
  * information about your computer - such as the web browser used and device type
  * your approximate geographic location based on your IP address

When you make an application we may ask for:

  * full contact details, including address, and mobile phone number
  * eligibility - nationality and immigration status
  * employment history 
  * qualifications, licences and professional memberships
  * diversity and inclusion information
  * CV and personal statement
  * Guaranteed Interview Scheme and reasonable adjustment requirements
  * National Insurance number (Home Office vacancies only)

When you are invited to an interview we may ask you to provide:

  * evidence of your identity and right to work in the UK - such as your passport, utility bills or other documentation

When you undergo pre-employment checks we may ask for:

  * contact details for your referees
  * National Insurance number
  * date of birth
  * public sector pension history
  * health declaration 
  * character declaration - including details of unspent convictions, motoring offences, police cautions, insolvency, bankruptcy, time spent outside of the UK and self-employment 
  * addresses for the last 5 years
  * passport details
  * driving licence details
  * previous names you have been known by

The list above only applies for applications made through the Civil Service Jobs system. Some advertisers may use their own application systems, when their privacy notice will apply.

When you contact us with feedback or an enquiry we will process:

  * your email address
  * the details of your request

## Purpose

The purposes for which we are processing your personal data are: 

  * to manage recruitment for Civil Service organisations and non-departmental public bodies. This includes a job board, online application service, sift tests, interview scheduling, and pre-employment checking service
  * to assess your suitability for a role
  * to enable the creation of user accounts
  * to provide SMS updates on the recruitment process
  * for civil servant candidate accounts, to allow users to view and apply for internal and across-government vacancies
  * to offer a job alert email service
  * to offer a priority mover service to help civil servants find new roles when they are at risk of redundancy
  * to provide technical support to candidates and recruiters
  * to monitor the effectiveness of recruitment processes - this could include statistical analysis of system usage, or research into the experience of applicants and other system users, or analysing referral sources to see which provide the most diverse applicants
  * to undertake pre-employment checking and onboarding activity before you start in a role in the Civil Service (including health, pension questionnaire, character declaration)
  * to comply with the [Baseline Personnel Security Standard (BPSS)](https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/government-baseline-personnel-security-standard) which consists of: 
    * verification of identity 
    * verification of nationality and immigration status - including entitlement to undertake the work in question
    * verification of employment history - through cross-referencing information against the HMRC PAYE system or through references 
    * verification of criminal record (unspent convictions) - for HMRC vacancies this check will also include spent convictions 
    * additional verification - only applies where additional verification or assurance is required

### Legal basis of processing 

The legal basis for processing your personal data is: 

  * Contractual: it is necessary for the performance of a contract to which you are a party - an employment contract. This relates to information that we need to recruit and employ you.
  * Contractual: it is necessary in order to take steps at your request prior to entering into a contract for employment. This relates to information that we collect as part of the application and selection process.
  * Legal obligation: it is necessary to comply with a legal obligation placed on us as the data controller - we are required to report on equality of opportunity; and onboarding processes have specific requirements
  * Public task: processing is necessary for the performance of a task carried out in the public interest or in the exercise of official authority vested in the data controller. In this case, Civil Service Jobs facilitates recruitment of high-quality candidates to roles across government departments, agencies and other public bodies. It provides recruitment tools and processes that support Civil Service recruitment strategy, and we also monitor the effectiveness of recruitment processes.

Sensitive personal data is personal data revealing racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, religious or philosophical beliefs, or trade union membership, and the processing of genetic data, biometric data for the purpose of uniquely identifying a natural person, data concerning health or data concerning a natural person's sex life or sexual orientation. 

The legal basis for processing your sensitive personal data is: 

  * it is necessary for reasons of substantial public interest for the exercise of a function of the Crown, a Minister of the Crown, or a government department; the exercise of a function conferred on a person by an enactment; the exercise of a function of either House of Parliament; or the administration of justice; and an appropriate policy document is in place. Civil Service Jobs facilitates recruitment of high-quality candidates to roles across government departments, agencies and other public bodies. It provides recruitment tools and processes that support Civil Service recruitment strategy. 
  * it is necessary for the purposes of performing or exercising our obligations or rights as the controller, or your obligations or rights as the data subject, under employment law, social security law or the law relating to social protection. External recruitment is required to follow the Civil Service Commission Recruitment Principles. Personal data is processed to ensure that these requirements are met. We are required under the Equality Act 2010 to make appropriate reasonable adjustments for candidates with a disability. 
  * processing is of a specific category of personal data and it is necessary for the purposes of identifying or keeping under review the existence or absence of equality of opportunity or treatment between groups of people specified (in paragraph 8(2) of Part 2 of Schedule 1 to the Data Protection Act 2018) in relation to that category with a view to enabling such equality to be promoted or maintained; and it is not carried out for the purposes of measures or decisions with respect to a particular data subject; and you have not declined consent; and you have not given notice that you do not wish your data to be processed for these purposes; and the processing is not likely to cause substantial damage or substantial distress to an individual. Diversity and inclusion data is used anonymously: ethnicity, religion, community background (Northern Ireland vacancies only), and sexual orientation. 
  * it is necessary for archiving purposes, scientific or historical research purposes or statistical purposes, and it is in the public interest. Analysis of applications and recruitment outcomes (including online tests), impact on protected groups, timescales for recruitment, and other research may be carried out.

The processing by us of personal data relating to criminal convictions and offences or related security measures is not carried out under official authority, but is authorised because it meets the following condition:

  * it is necessary for reasons of substantial public interest. This is ensuring that individuals with access to official information and assets will meet the required standards of propriety.

### Recipients

Your personal data will be shared by us with: 

Account data:

  * our technical supplier and their approved staff
  * our technical supplier's hosting provider
  * profiles may be shared with departments who have vacancies available for priority movers 

Once you have made an application, your information may be shared with:

  * approved staff managing vacancies (including recruiters and interview panel members)
  * Government Recruitment Service (GRS - managing recruitment on behalf of some recruiting departments)
  * the recruiting departments or profession
  * our technical supplier and their hosting provider
  * Capita
  * Government Recruitment Information Database (GRID)
  * Customer relationship management system
  * Email survey tools
  * Providers of individual leadership assessments, psychometric tests and staff engagement exercises
  * Civil Service Commission, Advisory Committee on Business Appointments, Office of the Commissioner for Public Appointments - to ensure that recruitment processes are correctly followed
  * The GOV.UK Notify service for sending text messages

If you meet the required standard but the recruiting department is unable to offer you the job, you may be given the option of being added to a reserve list. Reserve lists may be shared with other Civil Service departments who are recruiting for similar roles.

If you undergo pre-employment checks prior to appointment, your data may be shared with:

  * Government Recruitment Service
  * Customer relationship management system
  * Capita
  * Capita Security Watchdog
  * Disclosure and Barring Service
  * occupational health providers
  * Civil Service Pensions
  * the recruiting department 
  * the recruiting department’s shared service provider (if a third party supplier is used)

If you request support with your application or for a technical issue:

  * approved staff from Cabinet Office
  * approved staff from our technical supplier
  * customer relationship management system
  * project management tools
  * technical suppliers of online tests

As your personal data will be stored on our IT infrastructure it will also be shared with our data processors who provide email and document management and storage services to us. 

### Retention

Your personal data will be kept by us for the following durations:

Application records and associated files (including CVs, letters, emails, comment and feedback) will be deleted 2 years after the vacancy is archived. A vacancy becomes archived when there are no active applications and either:

  * the vacancy is manually archived by a recruiter; or 
  * the vacancy is automatically archived 1 year after the advertised closing date.

Candidate accounts - you can, at any time, choose to close your account. This will:

  * remove your ability to login to the account
  * withdraw any active applications
  * delete partially-completed applications which haven’t been submitted
  * disable the automatic sending of job alerts

Closed accounts are deleted and cannot be restored, however previously submitted applications will be retained until deletion for the period described above.

Candidate accounts that are active will remain in the system unless the candidate deletes them (or makes a request for deletion). An account will become inactive if the user has not logged in for two years. 

Vacancy manager accounts

ATS account holders are required to periodically reconfirm that they still require access, otherwise the account will become inactive.

Inactive accounts will be deleted three years after the last time the user logged in. Active accounts will remain in the system.

### Automated decision making 

Your personal data will be subject to automated decision making when online psychometric tests are used.

Some vacancies use online psychometric tests in the early stages of recruitment. Three tests are commonly used: Verbal Reasoning, Numerical Reasoning and the Civil Service Judgement Test. 

Decisions are made on who to invite to later stages based on automated scoring and sifting processes. In addition, test scores and other applicant data are regularly captured for statistical and research analysis purposes.

Your score is calculated from the responses you give during the test, and no other information about you is used. We compare your score to those gained by a peer group who previously took the test, to give you a percentile. The vacancy will have a minimum percentile requirement, and if your score is lower than this, you will be rejected and your application will not be considered further.

## Your rights

You have the right to request information about how your personal data is processed, and to request a copy of that personal data. 

You have the right to request a copy of any personal data you have provided, and for this to be provided in a structured, commonly used and machine-readable format. 

  * your personal data is available to view in your Application Centre at any time
  * you can request a copy of your personal data, in machine-readable format, by emailing [support.csjobs@cabinetoffice.gov.uk](mailto:support.csjobs@cabinetoffice.gov.uk) \- this request may take up to four weeks to process.

You have the right to request that any inaccuracies in your personal data are rectified without delay. 

  * you can edit your contact details in your Application Centre at any time
  * you can also edit contact details on submitted applications
  * to request corrections to an application you have submitted, email the contact listed on the advert for that vacancy - however only minor updates are usually considered

You have the right to request that any incomplete personal data are completed, including by means of a supplementary statement. 

  * you can add additional contact details via your Application Centre at any time
  * in most cases, you will be unable to submit an application if mandatory information is missing
  * please check your application carefully before submitting it, as your application will be assessed on the information you provide at that point

You have the right to request that your personal data is erased if there is no longer a justification for it to be processed. 

  * you can close your account at any time, from your Application Centre - this will: 
    * withdraw any submitted applications
    * delete any unsubmitted applications
    * stop job alerts being sent to you
    * delete your account data and remove your ability to log into your account again
  * any applications you have made in the past will be kept for audit purposes under our data retention policy

You have the right in certain circumstances (for example, where accuracy is contested) to request that the processing of your personal data is restricted. 

  * if your data is restricted from processing, you cannot be considered for a job
  * if your request relates to an application, email the contact listed on the job advert
  * if your request relates to your account, contact [support.csjobs@cabinetoffice.gov.uk](mailto:support.csjobs@cabinetoffice.gov.uk)

You have the right to object to the processing of your personal data where it is processed for direct marketing purposes. 

  * your data is not processed for direct marketing purposes

You have the right to object to the processing of your personal data.

  * you can object to processing, although you will then be unable to be considered for a job

You have the right, in relation to automatic profiling, to obtain human intervention in the outcome, to express your point of view, and to contest the decision reached by automatic profiling. 

  * you can email the contact listed on the advert for the job you have applied for

## International transfers

As your personal data is stored on our IT infrastructure, and shared with our data processors who provide email, and document management and storage services, it may be transferred and stored securely outside the European Economic Area. Where that is the case it will be subject to equivalent legal protection through the use of Model Contract Clauses.

## Complaints

If you consider that your personal data has been misused or mishandled, you may make a complaint to the Information Commissioner, who is an independent regulator. The Information Commissioner can be contacted at: 

Information Commissioner's Office  
Wycliffe House  
Water Lane  
Wilmslow  
Cheshire  
SK9 5AF  
0303 123 1113  

Any complaint to the Information Commissioner is without prejudice to your right to seek redress through the courts. 

## Contact details

Cabinet Office is the data controller for your account details, and for any applications you have not yet submitted.

Cabinet Office and the department you apply to are joint data controllers for your personal data within your submitted applications.

You can contact Civil Service Jobs by email: [support.csjobs@cabinetoffice.gov.uk](mailto:support.csjobs@cabinetoffice.gov.uk)

The contact details for Cabinet Office’s Data Protection Officer (DPO) are: 

Stephen Jones  
DPO  
Cabinet Office   
70 Whitehall  
London  
SW1A 2AS  

## Updates to this notice

If this privacy notice changes in any way, we will place an updated version on this page. Regularly reviewing this page ensures you are always aware of what information we collect, how we use it, and under what circumstances we will share it with other parties.

Last updated: 6 December 2019
